Ten years ago exactly,
Hace 10 años, exactamente,
I was in Afghanistan.
yo estaba en Afganistán.
I was covering the war in Afghanistan, and I witnessed, as a reporter for Al Jazeera,
Estaba cubriendo la guerra y fui testigo, como reportero de Al Jazeera,
the amount of suffering and destruction
del sufrimiento y la destrucción
that emerged out of a war like that.
que produce una guerra como esa.
Then, two years later,
Luego, dos años después,
I covered another war -- the war in Iraq.
cubría otra guerra, la de Irak.
I was placed at the center of that war
Yo estaba en medio de esa guerra
because I was covering the war
cubriendo lo que sucedía
from the northern part of Iraq.
en el norte de Irak.
And the war ended
Y la guerra terminó
with a regime change,
con un cambio de régimen
like the one in Afghanistan.
como el de Afganistán.
And that regime
Y ese régimen
that we got rid of
del que nos deshicimos
was actually a dictatorship,
en realidad era una dictadura,
an authoritarian regime,
un régimen autoritario,
that for decades
que durante décadas
created a great sense of paralysis
generó una gran parálisis
within the nation, within the people themselves.
en la nación y en las propias personas.
However,
Sin embargo,
the change that came through foreign intervention created even worse circumstances for the people
el cambio provocado por la intervención extranjera generó circunstancias aún peores para la gente
and deepened the sense
y profundizó el sentimiento
of paralysis and inferiority
de parálisis e inferioridad
in that part of the world.
en esa parte del mundo.
For decades,
Durante décadas
we have lived under authoritarian regimes --
hemos vivido bajo regímenes autoritarios
in the Arab world, in the Middle East.
en el mundo árabe, en Medio Oriente.
These regimes
Estos regímenes
created something within us during this period.
generaron algo dentro nuestro en este período.
I'm 43 years old right now.
Ahora tengo 43 años
For the last 40 years,
y en los últimos 40
I have seen almost the same faces
he visto casi los mismos rostros
for kings and presidents ruling us --
en los reyes y presidentes que nos gobiernan:
old, aged, authoritarian,
son viejos, ancianos, autoritarios,
corrupt situations --
vi actos de corrupción...
regimes that we have seen around us.
en los regímenes que nos rodeaban.
And for a moment I was wondering,
Y por un momento me preguntaba
are we going to live in order to see
si viviríamos para ver
real change happening on the ground,
un cambio real en el terreno,
a change that does not come through foreign intervention,
un cambio que no viniera de la intervención extranjera,
through the misery of occupation,
mediante la miseria de la ocupación,
through nations invading our land
producto de la invasión a nuestra tierra;
and deepening the sense of inferiority sometimes?
esa que agudizaría el sentimiento de inferioridad.
The Iraqis: yes, they got rid of Saddam Hussein,
Los iraquíes, sí, se deshicieron de Saddam Hussein
but when they saw
pero al ver
their land occupied by foreign forces they felt very sad,
su tierra ocupada por fuerzas extranjeras se sintieron muy mal;
they felt that their dignity had suffered.
sintieron que se resentía su dignidad.
And this is why they revolted.
Y por eso se rebelaron
This is why they did not accept. And actually other regimes, they told their citizens,
y no lo aceptaron. Y otros regímenes le dijeron a sus ciudadanos:
"Would you like to see the situation of Iraq?
"¿Quieren repetir la situación de Irak?
Would you like to see civil war, sectarian killing?
¿Quieren una guerra civil y asesinatos sectarios?
Would you like to see destruction?
¿Quieren la destrucción?
Would you like to see foreign troops on your land?"
¿Quieren ver tropas extranjeras en su tierra?"
And the people thought for themselves,
Y las personas pensaron para sus adentros:
"Maybe we should live with
"Quizá deberíamos permitir
this kind of authoritarian situation that we find ourselves in,
estas situaciones autoritarias y no vernos inmersos
instead of having the second scenario."
en un escenario como ese".
That was one of the worst nightmares that we have seen.
Esa fue una de las peores pesadillas que hemos visto.
For 10 years, unfortunately we have found ourselves
Durante 10 años por desgracia tuvimos que dar cuenta
reporting images of destruction,
de imágenes de destrucción,
images of killing,
de asesinatos,
of sectarian conflicts,
de conflictos sectarios,
images of violence,
imágenes de violencia
emerging from a magnificent piece of land,
en una tierra magnífica,
a region that one day was the source
una región que alguna vez fue cuna
of civilizations and art and culture
de civilizaciones, arte y cultura,
for thousands of years.
durante miles de años.
Now I am here to tell you
Ahora he venido a decirles
that the future
que el futuro
that we were dreaming for
que estábamos soñando
has eventually arrived.
finalmente ha llegado.
A new generation,
Una nueva generación
well-educated,
bien educada,
connected,
conectada,
inspired by universal values
inspirada en valores universales
and a global understanding,
y en una comprensión global
has created a new reality for us. We have found a new way
nos ha generado una nueva realidad. Hemos encontrado otra manera
to express our feelings
de expresar los sentimientos
and to express our dreams:
y los sueños.
these young people
Estos jóvenes
who have restored self-confidence
que han devuelto la auto confianza
in our nations in that part of the world,
a nuestras naciones en esa parte del mundo,
who have given us
que nos han dado
new meaning for freedom
un nuevo significado de libertad
and empowered us to go down to the streets.
y el poder para salir a las calles.
Nothing happened. No violence. Nothing.
No pasó nada. No hubo violencia. Nada.
Just step out of your house,
Fue solo salir de la casa
raise your voice and say, "We would like to see the end of the regime."
y en voz alta decir: "Nos gustaría ver el final del régimen".
This is what happened in Tunisia.
Esto es lo que sucedió en Túnez.
Over a few days,
En cuestión de días
the Tunisian regime that invested billions of dollars
el régimen tunecino que invirtió miles de millones de dólares
in the security agencies,
en organismos de seguridad
billions of dollars
miles de millones
in maintaining, trying to maintain,
para mantener -intentar mantener-
its prisons,
sus prisiones,
collapsed, disappeared,
colapsó, desapareció,
because of the voices of the public.
gracias a las voces del público.
People who were inspired to go down to the streets
Personas que inspiradas salieron a las calles
and to raise their voices,
a hacer escuchar sus voces
they tried to kill. The intelligence agencies wanted to arrest people.
arriesgando sus vidas. Los organismos de inteligencia quisieron arrestar a la gente.
They found something called Facebook.
Encontraron algo llamado Facebook.
They found something called Twitter.
Y algo llamado Twitter.
They were surprised by all of these kinds of issues. And they said,
Disgregaban estos temas diciendo:
"These kids are misled."
"Estos chicos están descarriados".
Therefore, they asked their parents
Por eso le pedían a sus padres
to go down to the streets
que salieran a las calles
and collect them, bring them back home.
a buscarlos para llevarlos de nuevo a casa.
This is what they were telling. This is their propaganda.
Eso era lo que decían. Esta era su propaganda:
"Bring these kids home
"Lleven a estos chicos a casa
because they are misled."
porque están descarriados".
But yes,
Pero sí,
these youth
estos jóvenes
who have been inspired
que han sido inspirados
by universal values,
en valores universales
who are idealistic enough
que son lo suficientemente idealistas
to imagine a magnificent future
para imaginar un futuro magnífico
and, at the same time, realistic enough
y, al mismo tiempo, lo suficientemente realistas
to balance this kind of imagination
como para equilibrar esta imaginación
and the process leading to it --
con el proceso que conduce a eso
not using violence, not trying to create chaos --
sin usar la violencia sin intentar crear caos.
these young people,
Estos jóvenes
they did not go home.
no se fueron a casa.
Parents actually went to the streets
Los padres salieron a las calles
and they supported them. And this is how the revolution was born in Tunisia.
a apoyarlos. Así fue como se gestó al revolución en Túnez.
We in Al Jazeera
Al Jazeera
were banned from Tunisia for years,
estuvo prohibida en Túnez durante años
and the government did not allow any Al Jazeera reporter to be there.
y el gobierno no permitió periodistas de Al Jazeera en el lugar.
But we found that these people in the street,
Pero encontramos que esta gente en las calles,
all of them are our reporters,
son todos periodistas nuestros,
feeding our newsroom
llenan nuestra redacción
with pictures, with videos
con fotos, videos
and with news.
y noticias.
And suddenly that newsroom in Doha
Y de repente esa redacción de Doha
became a center
se volvió el centro
that received all this kind of input from ordinary people --
receptor de todo este material de gente común,
people who are connected and people who have ambition
de gente que está conectada, que tiene ambiciones,
and who have liberated themselves
y que se ha liberado
from the feeling of inferiority.
del sentimiento de inferioridad.
And then we took that decision:
Y entonces tomamos la decisión
We are unrolling the news.
de cubrir la noticia.
We are going to be the voice for these voiceless people.
Vamos a ser la voz de los que no tienen voz.
We are going to spread the message.
Vamos a difundir el mensaje.
Yes, some of these young people are connected to the Internet,
Sí, algunos de estos jóvenes están conectados a Internet
but the connectivity in the Arab world
pero la conectividad en el mundo árabe
is very little, is very small,
es muy limitada, muy pequeña,
because of many problems that we are suffering from.
debido a los tantos problemas que padecemos.
But Al Jazeera took the voice from these people
Pero Al Jazeera tomó la voz de estas personas
and we amplified [it].
y la amplificó.
We put it in every sitting room in the Arab world --
La pusimos en cada sala de estar del mundo árabe
and internationally, globally,
e internacionalmente, a nivel mundial,
through our English channel.
por nuestro canal en inglés.
And then people started to feel
Y entonces la gente empezó a sentir
that there's something new happening.
que estaba pasando algo nuevo.
And then Zine al-Abidine Ben Ali decided to leave.
Y luego Zine al-Abidine Ben Ali decidió partir.
And then Egypt started,
Y luego comenzó Egipto
and Hosni Mubarak decided to leave.
y Hosni Mubarak decidió partir.
And now Libya as you see it.
Y ahora, como ven, es Libia.
And then you have Yemen. And you have many other countries trying to see
Y luego está Yemen. Y hay muchos otros países intentando ver
and to rediscover that feeling
y redescubrir ese sentimiento
of, "How do we imagine a future
de "¿Cómo imaginamos un futuro
which is magnificent and peaceful and tolerant?" I want to tell you something,
magnífico, en paz y tolerancia?" Quiero contarles algo
that the Internet and connectivity
y es que Internet y la conectividad
has created [a] new mindset. But this mindset
han creado un cambio de mentalidad. Pero este modo de pensar
has continued to be faithful
ha seguido siendo fiel
to the soil and to the land
al suelo y a la tierra
that it emerged from.
que lo vio nacer.
And while this was the major difference
Y si bien esta es una gran diferencia
between many initiatives before
respecto de muchas iniciativas previas
to create change,
de crear un cambio,
before we thought, and governments told us --
antes pensábamos -los gobiernos nos decían
and even sometimes it was true --
y a veces era verdad-
that change was imposed on us,
que nos habían impuesto los cambios
and people rejected that,
y que la gente rechazaba eso
because they thought that it is alien to their culture. Always, we believed
porque lo consideraba ajeno a su cultura, siempre creímos
that change will spring from within,
que el cambio iba a surgir del interior,
that change should be a reconciliation with culture, cultural diversity,
que el cambio debía ser una reconciliación con la cultura, con la diversidad cultural,
with our faith in our tradition
con la fe en nuestra tradición
and in our history,
y en nuestra historia
but at the same time,
pero al mismo tiempo
open to universal values, connected with the world,
debía estar abierto a valores universales, conectado al mundo,
tolerant to the outside.
tolerante con el afuera.
And this is the moment
Y eso es lo que
that is happening right now in the Arab world.
está sucediendo ahora mismo en el mundo árabe.
This is the right moment, and this is the actual moment
En este preciso instante, en este momento actual,
that we see all of these meanings meet together
vemos converger todos estos significados
and then create the beginning
y luego el inicio
of this magnificent era
de esta era magnífica
that will emerge from the region.
que va a surgir de la región.
How did the elite deal with that --
¿Cómo se lo tomó la élite,
the so-called political elite?
la denominada élite política?
In front of Facebook,
De cara a Facebook
they brought the camels in Tahrir Square.
llevaron los camellos a la Plaza Tahrir.
In front of Al Jazeera,
De cara a Al Jazeera
they started creating tribalism.
empezaron a crear el tribalismo.
And then when they failed, they started speaking about conspiracies
Y cuando no les resultó empezaron a hablar de conspiraciones
that emerged from Tel Aviv and Washington
emanadas de Tel Aviv
in order to divide the Arab world.
para dividir al mundo árabe.
They started telling the West,
Empezaron a decirle a Occidente:
"Be aware of Al-Qaeda.
"Atención con Al-Qaeda.
Al-Qaeda is taking over our territories.
Al-Qaeda se está apoderando de nuestros territorios.
These are Islamists
Son islamistas
trying to create new Imaras.
que intentan crear imaras.
Be aware of these people
Atención con esta gente
who [are] coming to you
que viene a arruinar
in order to ruin your great civilization."
nuestra gran civilización.
Fortunately, people right now cannot be deceived.
Por suerte la gente ya no se deja engañar.
Because this corrupt elite
Porque la élite corrupta
in that region
de esa región
has lost even the power of deception.
ha perdido hasta el poder de engaño.
They could not, and they cannot, imagine
No podían, y no pueden, imaginar
how they could really deal with this reality.
cómo hacer frente a esta realidad.
They have lost.
Han perdido...
They have been detached from their people, from the masses,
se han distanciado de sus pueblos, de las masas,
and now we are seeing them collapsing
y ahora vemos como se desploman
one after the other.
una tras otra.
Al Jazeera is not
Al Jazeera no es
a tool of revolution.
instrumento de revolución.
We do not create revolutions.
No creamos revoluciones.
However,
No obstante
when something of that magnitude happens,
cuando sucede algo de esa magnitud
we are at the center of the coverage.
estamos en el centro de la cobertura.
We were banned from Egypt,
Nos prohibieron en Egipto
and our correspondents,
y nuestros corresponsales,
some of them were arrested.
algunos fueron arrestados.
But most of our camera people
Pero muchos de nuestros camarógrafos
and our journalists,
y periodistas
they went underground in Egypt -- voluntarily --
pasaron a la clandestinidad en Egipto, voluntariamente,
to report what happened in Tahrir Square.
para informar de lo sucedido en la Plaza Tahrir.
For 18 days,
Durante 18 días
our cameras were broadcasting, live,
nuestras cámaras transmitieron en vivo
the voices of the people in Tahrir Square. I remember one night
las voces de la gente de la Plaza Tahrir. Recuerdo que una noche
when someone phoned me on my cellphone --
alguien me llamó al celular,
ordinary person who I don't know -- from Tahrir Square.
una persona común que no conozco, desde la Plaza Tahrir.
He told me, "We appeal to you
Me dijo: "Le solicitamos
not to switch off the cameras. If you switch off the cameras tonight,
que no apague las cámaras. Si apaga las cámaras esta noche
there will be a genocide.
va a haber un genocidio.
You are protecting us
Ud nos está protegiendo
by showing what is happening at Tahrir Square."
al mostrar lo que sucede en la Plaza Tahrir".
I felt the responsibility
Sentí la responsabilidad
to phone our correspondents there
de llamar a nuestros corresponsales
and to phone our newsroom
y a la sala de redacción
and to tell them, "Make your best
y de decirles "Hagan lo posible
not to switch off the cameras at night,
para no apagar las cámaras esta noche
because the guys there really feel confident
porque los muchachos de la plaza sienten confianza
when someone is reporting their story --
si alguien cubre la noticia;
and they feel protected as well."
así se sienten protegidos".
So we have a chance to create a new future
Así que tenemos la oportunidad de crear un nuevo futuro
in that part of the world.
en esa parte del mundo.
We have a chance
Tenemos la oportunidad
to go and to think of the future as something which is open to the world.
de ir y pensar el futuro como algo abierto al mundo.
Let us not repeat the mistake of Iran,
No repitamos los errores de Irán
of [the] Mosaddeq revolution.
de la revolución...
Let us free ourselves -- especially in the West --
Dejemos -sobre todo en Occidente-
from thinking about that part of the world
de pensar en esa parte del mundo
based on oil interest,
en base al petróleo
or based on interests
o interesados
of the illusion of stability and security.
en la ilusión de estabilidad y seguridad.
The stability and security
La estabilidad y la seguridad
of authoritarian regimes
de los regímenes autoritarios
cannot create but terrorism and violence and destruction.
no pueden crear más que terrorismo, violencia y destrucción.
Let us accept the choice of the people.
Aceptemos la elección de la gente.
Let us not pick and choose
No pongamos a dedo
who we would like to rule their future. The future should be ruled
a quien nos gustaría que gobierne su futuro. El futuro debería estar en manos
by people themselves,
de la propia gente
even sometimes if they are voices
incluso si son, como ahora, voces
that might now scare us.
que puedan asustarnos.
But the values of democracy
Pero los valores democráticos
and the freedom of choice
y la libertad de elección
that is sweeping the Middle East at this moment in time
que se extiende por Medio Oriente en este momento
is the best opportunity for the world,
es la mejor oportunidad para el mundo,
for the West and the East, to see stability and to see security
para Oriente y Occidente, de ver estabilidad, seguridad,
and to see friendship and to see tolerance
de ver amistad y tolerancia
emerging from the Arab world,
en el mundo árabe,
rather than the images of violence and terrorism.
en vez de ver imágenes de violencia y terrorismo.
Let us support these people.
Apoyemos a estas personas.
Let us stand for them.
Démosles una mano
And let us give up
y renunciemos
our narrow selfishness in order to embrace change,
a nuestro egoísmo corto de miras para abrazar el cambio
and in order to celebrate with the people of that region
y festejar con la gente de esa región
a great future
un gran futuro,
and hope and tolerance. The future has arrived,
la paz y la esperanza. El futuro ha llegado,
and the future is now.
el futuro es ahora.
I thank you very much.
Les agradezco mucho.
(Applause)
(Aplausos)
Thank you very much.
Muchas gracias.
Chris Anderson: I just have a couple of questions for you.
Chris Anderson: sólo tengo un par de preguntas.
Thank you for coming here. How would you characterize the historical significance
Gracias por venir. ¿Cómo describirías la importancia histórica
of what's happened?
de lo sucedido?
Is this a story-of-the-year, a story-of-the-decade
¿Es la historia del año, la historia de la década,
or something more?
o es algo más?
Wadah Khanfar: Actually, this may be the biggest story that we have ever covered.
Wadah Khanfar: En realidad es la historia más importante que hayamos cubierto.
We have covered many wars.
Hemos estado en muchas guerras.
We have covered a lot of tragedies, a lot of problems,
Hemos cubierto muchas tragedias, muchos problemas,
a lot of conflict zones, a lot of hot spots in the region,
muchas zonas de conflicto, muchos conflictos en la región,
because we were centered at the middle of it.
porque estábamos en medio de eso.
But this is a story -- it is a great story; it is beautiful.
Pero en este caso es una gran historia; es hermosa.
It is not something that you only cover
No es algo que uno tiene que cubrir
because you have to cover a great incident.
porque así lo hace siempre con los grandes sucesos.
You are witnessing change in history.
Uno está presenciando un cambio histórico.
You are witnessing the birth of a new era.
Está presenciando el nacimiento de una era.
And this is what the story's all about.
De eso se trata esta historia.
CA: There are a lot of people in the West
CA: Muchas personas en Occidente
who are still skeptical,
todavía son escépticos
or think this may just be an intermediate stage
o piensan que puede tratarse de un período intermedio
before much more alarming chaos.
antes de un caos mucho más alarmante.
You really believe
¿Crees realmente
that if there are democratic elections in Egypt now,
que si ahora hay elecciones democráticas en Egipto
that a government could emerge
pueda surgir un gobierno que propugne
that espouses some of the values you've spoken about so inspiringly?
algunos de los valores tan inspiradores de los que has hablado?
WK: And people actually,
WK: En realidad la gente
after the collapse of the Hosni Mubarak regime,
luego del colapso del régimen de Hosni Mubarak,
the youth who have organized themselves
los jóvenes que se han auto-organizado
in certain groups and councils,
en ciertos grupos y concejos,
they are guarding the transformation
están velando por la transformación
and they are trying to put it on a track
tratando de encaminarla
in order to satisfy
para satisfacer
the values of democracy,
los valores democráticos
but at the same time also to make it reasonable
pero al mismo tiempo también para que sea razonable
and to make it rational,
y para que sea racional,
not to go out of order.
para que no se salga de control.
In my opinion, these people are much more wiser than, not only the political elite,
Opino que estas personas son mucho más sabias no sólo que la élite política
even the intellectual elite, even opposition leaders
sino que la élite intelectual y que los líderes opositores
including political parties.
incluyendo a los partidos políticos.
At this moment in time, the youth in the Arab world are much more wiser
En este momento la juventud del mundo árabe es mucho más sabia
and capable of creating the change
y capaz de crear el cambio
than the old --
que los viejos
including the political and cultural
-incluyendo al viejo régimen político
and ideological old regimes.
cultural e ideológico.
(Applause)
(Aplausos)
CA: We are not to get involved politically and interfere in that way.
CA: No vamos a entrometernos políticamente ni interferir en ese sentido.
What should people here at TED,
¿Qué debería hacer la gente en TED,
here in the West,
aquí en Occidente,
do if they want to connect or make a difference
si quisiera conectarse para marcar una diferencia
and they believe in what's happening here?
si creen en lo que está pasando aquí?
WK: I think we have discovered a very important issue in the Arab world -- that people care,
WK: creo que hemos descubierto algo muy importante en el mundo árabe: que a la gente
people care about this great transformation.
le importa esta gran transformación.
Mohamed Nanabhay who's sitting with us,
Mohamed Nanabhay que está entre nosotros,
the head of Aljazeera.net, he told me that a 2,500 percent increase
el jefe de aljazeera.net, me dijo que se incrementó 2500%
of accessing our website
el acceso a nuestro sitio
from various parts of the world.
desde varias partes del mundo.
Fifty percent of it is coming from America.
El 50% del total viene de EE.UU.
Because we discovered that people care,
Descubrimos que a la gente le importa,
and people would like to know --
la gente quiere saber,
they are receiving the stream through our Internet.
están recibiendo la señal por Internet.
Unfortunately in the United States, we are not covering but Washington D.C. at this moment in time
Desafortunadamente en EE.UU. en este momento sólo estamos en Washington D.C.
for Al Jazeera English.
para Al Jazeera en inglés.
But I can tell you, this is the moment to celebrate
Pero puedo decirles que es el momento de festejar
through connecting ourselves with those people in the street
conectándonos con esas personas en la calle,
and expressing our support to them
es momento de expresarles nuestro apoyo
and expressing this kind of feeling, universal feeling,
y ese sentimiento universal
of supporting the weak and the oppressed
de apoyo al débil y al oprimido
to create a much better future for all of us.
para crear un futuro mucho mejor para todos.
CA: Well Wadah, a group of members of the TED community,
CA: Bien Wadah, un grupo de miembros de la comunidad de TED,
TEDxCairo, are meeting as we speak.
TEDxCairo, están reunidos mientras hablamos.
They've had some speakers there.
Tuvieron algunos oradores allí.
I believe they've heard your talk.
Creo que han escuchado tu charla.
Thank you for inspiring them and for inspiring all of us.
Gracias por ser de inspiración para ellos y para nosotros.
Thank you so much. (Applause)
Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)